dr. John Gervais key is an award-winning
lecturer at the University of Toronto
from the department's of psychology
cognitive science and Buddhist
psychology he's done a few TED Talks and
he's rising in popularity now for work
on a meaning crisis and that's what
we're going to focus on today so first
of all what is the meaning crisis so the
meaning crisis is an intersection of
sort of perennial problems that human
beings face and some specific historical
circumstances that we're in in the West
the perennial problems are basically
under an umbrella the idea is the
cognitive processes that make us
adaptive that give us our intelligence
to put a a single turn on it term on it
also are the very same processes that
make us continually prone and libel to
self deceptive self-destructive behavior
so across cultures and crossed
historical context people have come up
with various sets of practices for
trying to ameliorate those aspects of
self-deception and self-destruction and
in addition what they try to do is not
only ameliorate the way that
self-destructive self-deceptive behavior
makes us fit our environment maladaptive
ly maybe connect to our own agency
maladaptive ly connect to other people
maladaptive ly connect to our particular
circumstances maladaptive Li not only
those practices try to ameliorate that
they try to also do the reverse in
addition to reducing the foolishness of
self-deception they try to afford an
enhanced sense of connectedness so that
one feels one is fully alive fully
agentic fully connected to the world
fully connected to others fully
connected to a course of transformation
and growth and development and so those
sets of practices that ameliorate
foolishness and afford meaning in life
there broadly understood as wisdom
practices and what's happened in the
West is for various historical reasons
and now we have shift from the perennial
problems to the historical factors
reverse historical reasons a worldview
that gave us an understanding of these
practices valorized them gave us
guidance gave us established
institutions and traditions basically
that had you know a wisdom culture for
us has largely disappeared so well of
course we have tremendous knowledge and
information progress if that's the right
word I might call it into question later
but we we have very much a wisdom famine
and so people have very shallow
resources in general for dealing with
self-deception till self-destructive
behavior and for enhancing and affording
increased meaning in life and those
historical forces are complex and I go
over them at length in the meeting
crisis but we are basically suffering a
wisdom and meaning famine because we
don't have a worldview that tells us how
our wisdom practices should fit together
I wish you'd collect them how we should
curate them how we should correct them
how we should communicate them with each
other we don't have a worldview that
gives us a cognitive existential and
even ultimately sort of metaphysical
grounding for our cultivations of wisdom
and meaning so we have this scientific
worldview in which we don't find any
kind of home so Christopher master
Pietro and Philip mr. that can I call
this kind of like a cultural Dhamma side
Dhamma side is when you lose your sense
of being at home of belonging of fitting
fitting in not in the conformity sense
but fitting being in continuity of
contact with what's real and what really
matters and so there's two aspects to
the meaning crisis there's a perennial
one and you'll see it in literature
across the ages people worry about
falling into despair or finding life
empty
way that things are meaningless and and
what's happened is the perennial
responses to that have been seriously
undermined in a culture for a lot of
historical reasons and then they've been
exacerbated and accelerated increase of
a technological framing of of who we are
and what the world is we see everything
basically as objects and resources to be
manipulated and controlled and then that
aligns with you know a pervasive market
mentality in which the only sort of
normative Authority that still left is
the market for people a sense of
everything being commodified everything
being as everything's being sold and
there's and I'll use this term in a
technical sense there's so much
everywhere and and this has pervaded our
political and cultural arena so not only
do we are we wisdom and meaning
impoverished we also feel a set by a lot
of forces that seem to be degrading our
basic sense of our humanity so that's
what I would call the meeting crisis
okay that's a great start I just want to
summarize it or super simplify it
sure so if I simplify it too much you
can let me know and we'll work at it I
want to get like I want to get really
shortly okay you know because
potentially I could actually you know
talk to my students about this we're in
middle school although it like you
mentioned the West earlier and I it does
seem like this is not really happening
in the East although maybe it's starting
to happen it's definitely happening in
Japan it's definitely happening in Japan
so you see the next generation coming up
but there's a whole class of people that
have sort of retreated from society of
young people and retreated into the
virtual world because they find that
world has many of the features that the
real world is lacking for them so it's
definitely the case in Japan but I don't
know about other places
in the in the East okay okay excellent
so and yeah I agree there definitely
seems to be something happening in Japan
there okay so um you used the word
cognitive faculties I think I will just
I would just summarize that as maybe the
mind it's like sure we have a mind and
it's it's an incredible tool it's also
you know
alright I'm already talking too much we
have a mind it can it can help us to
grow and connect with the world or we
can use it badly and then our life
similarly turns for the worse and then
we we also have this you know culture
and mythos mythology that that can help
that not only gives us the tools to
properly use our mind but like a
narrative framework so that we know who
we are and what we're doing why we're
here and the meaning crisis is is most
specifically the dissolution of that
kind of culture the wisdom culture yes
yeah very much yeah fine with that okay
so I'm gonna try and simplify it even
more now
okay there's wisdom that's good and we
also know that lack of wisdom is bad and
there needs to be a culture for of
wisdom and for wisdom so that as a
society we can stick together and that
wisdom culture is rapidly decaying in
the West and other places yes although
there are clear signs of people
increasingly trying to revive it so
there's so there's sort of negative
symptoms of the meaning crisis the way
people are suffering a loss of agency
and suffering a lot
a sense of belonging to being there's
the negative symptoms but there's also
positive symptoms in which you see
people trying to bring back stoicism and
create these these like what we're
having right now these new ways of
carrying out you know what I would
ultimately call philosophical discourse
we're not just talking we're not just
doing something you know to get
something done we're trying to work on
the meaning of things and the meaning of
who and what we are so I mean it in that
sense that ancient sense of philosophy
but I sometimes call philosophy a-- and
so you see also uh you know and you know
the mindfulness revolution there's
criticisms of it but it's nevertheless
people are trying to put together wisdom
practices now what we're discovering is
that because again of our particular
historical past we're tending to do this
in a very fragmented and autodidactic
and egocentric way which everybody is
sort of on their own trying to cultivate
their own little wisdom philosophy
wisdom religion and and you know and and
I don't wanna I don't wanna I don't want
to just completely dismiss that because
people are trying to ameliorate their
suffering and afford meaning and that's
a good thing but you know the worst
things can come from the best things
turned bad what I mean by that is this
tends to create a really fragmented
autodidact ism fragments us from other
people so we can't we need we have to
work collectively to build an
alternative worldview right the idea
that you know the idea that you can have
your own worldview I think is a serious
form of because it's it refer
it sort of ramps up that that that ego
centrism and that being locked inside
your head and your own subjectivity and
breeds narcissism and other things like
that because when you're when you're
autodidactic all those proclivities
towards self-deception and
self-destructive behavior don't have
anything counterbalancing them oh one
second just give me your definition of
autodidactic autodidactic is you do it
on your own
without entering into any kind of
sustained community or tradition that
provides you with a framework that can
be obscene as more encompassing and
challenging to your own personal
egocentric framework so what's the
what's the opposite of autodidactic the
opposite of autodidactic would be to to
belong to community with some kind of
tradition some kind of collective
intelligence being shared amongst
distributed cognition so that we can
collectively create these ecologies of
practices and create an a an alternative
worldview that will properly hone them
okay
that's why these discussions are so
important and part of what we're seeing
right now in a particular crisis were in
with the virus right is we one of the I
mean and I don't want to make light of
this people are dying it's I take that
seriously so I'm not trying to put that
aside but that's not the core of what
we're talking about here so I'm asking
for people to understand that right but
one of the things that it's revealing to
people is how much how actually
important because it was so back rounded
but how much connecting to others in a
significant way and working with others
and being present with others how much
it really matters to us how deeply and
we tended look we walked around outside
and we were like inside but can blocked
in and then we're realizing oh Jesus I
actually don't want to be locked in like
that I really need to connect to the
world to get outside of the prison of my
own ego to can open myself up to other
people in you know in in various degrees
of depth and and so I think what what
we're seeing is how important that kind
of deep connectedness really is it was
it's been so back rounded by our
busyness and by our technology and now
the crisis is revealing how in
important it is and how actually it's
going to be something we really need to
enhance if we want to get through this
in the best possible way okay I do want
to talk about stoicism and my own
personal experience there but the first
I feel like I should stick to my word
with what I said in our re first email
exchange the second question how do we
get out of the meaning crisis and so to
use our earlier definition how do we
I guess bring back a wisdom culture yeah
well I mean the there's two ways of
thinking you should do that one is what
you might call a top-down where
somebody's gonna construct some system
where religion and then impose it on
people the other is to just sort of hope
that things are going to percolate
bottom-up various groups of people are
gonna somehow start forming communities
get together I think both of those
Express ood exclusively as a mistake so
one of the things we need to do is
there's all these emerging communities
and that's great but we need to get them
talking and not only do we need to
improve the depth of what they're
talking about we need to improve the
depth of how they're talking to each
other so I'm doing a lot of work with
Peter Limburg and Christopher master
Pietro and guys tense talk and other
people right and you see a lot of work
not you know I taught forms like rebel
wisdom and future thinkers voice Club
where people are trying to transform how
we use dialog to afford the cultivation
of wisdom and use that as a way of
trying to start to create a culture that
can then act as a home within which we
can collect curate correct and vet
Ecology's of practices now that brings
me to the second point I don't think you
should look for one practice one thing
to do to ameliorate the meaning crisis I
think you need to do
a bunch of things I need I think you
need no first of all you need this kind
of practice what I call the Chris and I
called dialectic where you really put
dialog so we can just talk and then
dialogue is when we're trying to connect
and then dialectic is where we're trying
to collect connect so we can do
philosophy it together so that we can
cultivate wisdom together right right
dialectic obviously to create that
cultural home but we also need you know
meditative practices contemplative
practices movement practices right so we
need you know that's why I talk to
people like Rafe Kelly and the
extraordinary work he's doing on putting
together you know what ecology of
practices and his evolved move play
framework so we need to create ecologies
of practices because no one practiced
your cognition your mind is such an
incredibly dynamic and self-organizing
thing right you need you need something
you need a set of practices that are
also incredibly dynamic and
self-organizing to properly try to
transform your mind in the comprehensive
and deep way we need to in order to
start ameliorating the meeting crisis
excellent and just to add on to that
last point so you know you're talking
about an ecology of practices which it
kind of reminds me of like diversifying
a portfolio that might be a bad analogy
but another effective method for me has
been finding one practice and then kind
of like like doing it in as many
different ways as possible yep
introduced variation I mean that's how
you watched little kids that's how they
learn right so if they're doing some
tasks they'll come up with a strategy
that solves the task solves the problem
gets them to the goal but they won't
initially stick with that what they'll
do is they'll create all kinds of
variations alternative strategies and
then they'll put them into competition
with each other in terms of you know
maybe efficiency or which one most
pleases mom or which one best connects
them to their peers and so they do
something that's very analogous to
biological evolution right they will
dude variation and then they'll put some
selective pressure on it until they
settle onto a strategy and then they'll
vary on that again by the way I think
that's an important model for how your
how your cognition how your mind
fundamentally gets a grip on the world
is that process of variation and
selection and evolve continually
evolving it's fitted 'no stew the world
and so i think that is exactly how you
should so not only should you have a
call so you should have practices that
have complimentary sets and weaknesses
right we talked about that a minute ago
then you should do what you just said
you should evolve each practice and they
should also think about practices that
Ridgid bridge between the various
practices that help you better sort of
transition from one context to another
okay that's great
but we still need the overarching
culture for the wisdom culture and you
can't do that as an individual yeah
culture is not something trying to
invent your own culture with you is like
trying to invent your own language it
doesn't make any sense it doesn't make
any sense it's a deeply mistaken thing
to do yeah right and so the only way
we're going to do that is if we become
aware if we if we give up the idea that
we are isolated atomic individuals in
our head and our subjectivity is all
that really matters right and what we
need to do is to get back to the fact
that most of our
he's done like the way we networked
minds together the way the Internet
networks commute computers together
culture networks minds together so that
they can solve these huge Titanic
problems we're facing one right now that
we can't do a damn thing against as
individuals but we need to get as much
right distributed cognition working
together and as much of that distributed
collective intelligence we gotta get it
operating as rationally and I said as
wisely as possible and we need to do a
lot of work to get that collective
intelligence up to collective wisdom
that's the product now it's doable it is
very doable and the things that have
done that in the past have been
religions religions have brought about
that tremendous transformation of
consciousness cognition character and
ultimately culture it needs something
analogous in this discourse unless I'm
not proposing a religion but we need
something analogous to religion in order
in this collective discourse to create
an there's a deep connection between
cult and culture you can hear it in the
word they're bound together cultists
right one thing I thought of which I I
guess I haven't thought of before as a
as a way to cultivate a dialectic well
the big problem I have is with these
social media platforms like Facebook
even though you know I really I'm
totally capable of discourse and
dialectic but you know you started with
up with a long comment and then it gets
shorter and shorter and more and more
divisive you know we've even among like
you know two really smart calm relaxed
intellectual people so I think well one
thing we definitely need isn't is a new
platform and we don't really have a good
platform I was thinking like maybe read
it maybe forms there's something there
but it's like but even even if we look
at all of these like communication
platforms I still feel like even if we
find one good one there
would still be like an overarching
culture that I guess it has to grow
organically right and we have to do it
it isn't all organically that's the
bottom up but it also needs to be
informed by our best historical and
scientific understanding that's the
top-down aspect need to be doing both at
the same time I think one of what I was
trying to put my finger on earlier is
one of the things Co bit 19 is showing
us is it's putting a gloomy and
evolutionary metaphor it's putting
selective pressure on us to come up with
the alternative ways in which we can
carry out deep discourse that would
afford something like dialectic where
we're trying to figure out basically how
do we keep a society and a culture
running through you know these kind of
communicative platforms I think people
who let's let's be really brutally
honest this isn't going to be the only
pandemic we're gonna be facing the
causes of this have not gone away the
biological you know the permafrost
melting the rainforests being cut down
human concentration and massive global
is like all the none of those factors
have gone away alright so this is not
gonna be the only time this is gonna
happen to us and so I think the people
who this is I guess the people who
figure out how to do what you're talking
about how to figure out how to get this
into a more comprehensive collective
platform you know where we can carry out
this kind of dialectic right and we can
scale it up and down the way we used to
do like with with with with religion
that person will be those people will be
enormous little wealthy I would think
this is an opportunity if people are
looking for a business opportunity a
business opportunity that could hope to
change the course of history in a
positive direction this is the place to
go right and you and I are doing that at
this very moment
so YouTube that's the one platform or
isn't thinking of so we're doing what
we're doing it a lot with YouTube and
YouTube is I think really good at it
and I'm using it a lot as a platform
the problem with YouTube is it's
tends to be passive participation for
the vast majority of people yes right
and so you need to be able to you need
to you're either you're either in you're
either you know you're either the person
on the YouTube channel or you're a
passive observer I mean you make
comments but you know I mean which
they're doing a little bit more we're
doing premiering which is a really good
idea and people you know chat well um
something's on YouTube there's also
creating watch parties I know the future
thinker did quite a few of those for my
awakening for the meaning crisis where
people watch the videos together and
then of a video a you know group video
chat and talk about it
which i think is an excellent idea I see
that I see it evolving but it's still
like this you know what I mean it's all
over but somebody needs to sort of hey
here's how we could but not somebody's
you know smoothly it's gonna be a group
of people say but here's how we could
coordinate this all together right kind
of reminds me of my music festival days
you know you're just in the middle of
nowhere
and India is like this also the Hulk
India is like a music festival that's
the best way I describe it is it just
it's complete chaos but it you know they
all they're peaceful right but then it's
just the energy just kind of like builds
up from like the collective minds until
eventually some leader just emerges and
says okay guys we're doing this my voice
is louder than you and they go yeah
let's do that well I mean so that means
there's a danger to all of what we're
talking about of course because there's
an opportunity for people to manipulate
others because of the hunger for meaning
and because of the hunger for home
cultural home so yeah I think we have to
be also very vigilant about that we want
to pick leaders who have given us good
evidence and good plausible reason that
they are deeply committed from a place
of Integra
towards wisdom and meaning that's what
we have to that's what we have to make
central not that they initially make us
feel good right right okay so let's talk
about religion so one thing is your dad
many times before is like people are
looking for a religion that isn't the
religious right the religion that's not
a religion yeah yeah so to me that
sounds like the well it sounds like
exactly what I'm doing basically which
is go along it's God but no church yeah
yeah so that's what a lot of what the so
called nuns NO NES we're doing right so
they don't they don't for largely for we
haven't gone into them we keep alluding
for them all after you do it again but
your your listeners can know that you
know I do discuss this at length in the
series but for a lot of historical
reasons and and and some current reasons
many people have sort of turned their
back on the organized religions various
kinds this isn't just you know
particular to Christianity for example
in a sense that and here's the thing
that with the whole new atheism movement
missed the New Atheism movement was all
about well you know what's happening is
that people are disbelieving in God or
the sacred or something like that that's
not the case with you
put yourself out as an example so I'm
going to use you okay and so no that's
not the case it's not that these people
are atheists it's that they find and
this is a much more important point they
find that the traditional frameworks the
traditional religions non-viable they
don't connect and if my argument is
right what people are deeply deeply
looking for when they turn to a religion
is to enhance that sense of
connectedness and to give them something
that's viable and workable in their
lives for overcoming self-deception and
a forty meeting and they're not
they're basically saying to the churches
and the temples and the mosques and etc
you don't do that for me
anymore and they also reject what we
tried in the 20th century which was you
know you know pseudo religious
ideologies like you know Nazism and
communism and think we they reject those
because they saw the way they drench the
world in blood finally if you allow me
one more point is that you know you
can't people try to deny that but you
can't deny the importance of Science and
Technology and you can't separate them
they're not identical but science and
technology are woven together they're
married together I mean that a very
strong sense of the word but that we're
relying on science and technology for us
to even have met to even have this
conversation and if you try to pretend
that that pervasive worldview is not
seeped into the guts of your mind
that's a deep form of self-deception so
you what you need is you need something
right that gives people in I'll use that
term ecology practices that that's
viable to them that they can somehow
live with while they live in a
scientific hyper technological world
right and gives them a real sense of
enhancing their connectedness and
enhancing their capacity to grow
overcome self-deception to self
transcend so that's what a lot of people
how people are doing it to various
degrees of effectiveness some people do
that to escape they go into virtual
games where they find already set
narrative and they find a ready set you
know worldview that makes sense and has
rules and they find it ready set way of
self transcending and leveling up some
people escape other people choose to
stay I think that's what you referring
with to and you refer to yourself and
try and somehow make it work but the
problem for that is again the problem
with what many people are doing is they
as I said before it you can get isolated
can be autodidactic it can be fragmented
and and that that's also something that
ultimately frustrates people in kind of
a profound way because part of the
connectedness you're looking for is not
just a deeper connectedness to yourself
and the world it's deeper connectedness
to other people and that that's very
hard to do and so that's what I'm
talking about when I'm talking about the
religion it's not a religion okay yeah
religion is is like the fundamental
thing that like it's it's the problem
and the solution it seems yes that is
very well said
that's we're saying again it is both
that's what I'm trying to capture with
the religion that's not a religion
insofar as it's a solution we need what
we're talking to be a religion but
insofar as traditional religion is a
problem when you get to not be a
religion that's exactly what I'm trying
to convey with that phrase but you put
it nicely it's both the solution and the
problem so maybe do you mind if I share
some personal experience please
so I'm unbelievably fortunate in my life
but speaking just on religion I was 24
25 and I wandered into my apartment and
I saw a copy of the Bhagavad Gita on
like my countertop there never heard of
it before which is strange right because
I didn't like it I used to be a hardcore
intellectual now I'm more into just I'm
just not like nerdy about it I guess no
you know it's a habit so I can't fully
kick it but um and I don't want to but
so anyway I picked it up and I was like
whoa this is so cool and I read the
whole damn thing every verse and
literally a month or two a couple months
later I actually met Krishna like inside
myself and in your antistick experience
a very profound mystical experience and
that's why I'm in China now because
shortly after that
I lost all my friends they all thought I
was crazy and I found myself in Thailand
teaching English on a whim you know but
but here's here's where it gets really
interesting so I I can't believe how
this happened so I read the Gita and and
I like I understood it all and and I was
able to like incorporate the wisdom
without ever meeting another devotee a
church a temple anything but it but I
still like it it can't last forever so a
couple years ago I said I had to go to
India and I got to go to like the home
birthplace of this and that's what I did
and some pretty bad experiences there so
I yeah like um I I so I went to take a
beginner disciple course this is like
the most level 0 level one I could find
which was a total cost of five dollars
for a three day course I don't know what
it is in rupees but you know very cheap
level one course they rejected me and so
and I mean as soon as that happened I
was like I was so in shock I was so
humbled which is actually a good thing
like humility is like very good
spiritual virtue right so it's
ultimately it's ultimately helped me a
lot but I've learned to kind of like
like do Krishna do God unlike my own
like like I'm still like I have friends
who are you know practicing as I am but
I'm not just going to like give a
thousand dollars to the church to you
know like yeah and and also just final
in closing so I've always been against
dogma in general and organized religion
in all institutions I've never had an
attraction here but what's interesting
happened
to me as I'm I'm now even more against
it I think they melt then a lot of nuns
and but I'm actually very religious I
practice I shan't almost 2,000 mantras
every day right that's that's more that
that's a couple hours it's the only
thing in my life that I that I do
strictly everything else I might change
a little bit you know I changed the time
I brush my teeth and different things
but every single day this is one thing I
do and ya can't respond to that because
I think part of the tell you what the
religion that's not a religion is again
not to is not to try and create a single
thing it what what I what I'm trying to
talk about is a culture maybe you know
where there you as you know as a devotee
a the whole you know wisdom traditions
surrounding Krishna right Hindu usually
using a version of the dantana right
yeah yeah that you can enter into deep
communion communication and community
people perhaps coming from a stoic
tradition or people coming from a
Christian tradition or people who write
or not of any particular tradition but
their mystical experience was of the
emptiness that from without within
Buddhism or the glory of God
you know that's associated with perhaps
aspects of the Sufi tradition or
something like that that's what I'm
talking about I'm talking about not
getting everybody to share a set of
dogmas that's part of what we have to
give up you have to give up the idea of
a shared set of doctrines as what Minds
us together and instead can we go back
to the idea of a shared set of processes
look we've done this in the secular
world although it's breaking down right
now we figured out that we don't have to
all share the same view right what we
have to do is all be committed to the
same processes of democracy self
correction you know legal proceedings we
have to commit and share and what's
happening is we're losing that sense of
that which i think is very dangerous
first right now but right and we're
trying to shift back to like what's
happening to something the United States
we're trying to get know everybody
should believe the same thing which i
think is a disastrous idea instead of
it's no no you and I can believe
different things but we both share a
commitment to a process that we think is
more important than our individual views
because the process itself is before us
and after us and it's self-corrects and
it affords our self correction and part
of the difficulty I see that's happening
right now is we're losing that ability
to commit to the process and a shared
commitment to the process of
communication and communion and
collective intelligence and distributed
cognition and we're going back to right
there's old model which i think is a
disastrous idea no no we got have we got
to all believe the same thing and I so I
I want to be really clear that I'm not
proposing that you know everybody should
be a devotee of Krishna or Christ or
Siddhartha Gautama or Socrates I'm
proposing we need you know we need what
we in fact what they even had in the
ancient world in the West they had for
wisdom schools you know the the Platonic
the Aristotelian or the stoic and
epicurean and they all got along
together they were all mutually
supported by the Roman Empire right and
I think that's the kind of thing I'm
trying to talk about because I I think
we need only need an ecology of
practices we need an ecology of
communities and one of the things that
I'm grateful for is growing up in Canada
where we have before hey very good
historical reasons we have a long
tradition and I people II believe in you
know of multiculturalism as an idea
where you can have two communities
living together because of a shared
commitment to processes of communication
communing and collective intelligence
can I share another experience
so I guess maybe the first big mystical
experience I had was reading Aristotle
next room yeah I was 16 and which
treatise the ethics Nicomachean ethics
yeah of course I was also really lucky I
got the best translation because you
know these with all these ancient texts
the translation is so fundamental it's
so important years years later I tried
reading a different translation I
couldn't get through the first page I
was like this sucks you know but I'm the
good no totally the translation really
matters yeah I had a similar experience
when I read the Republic by Plato for
the first time excellent well this this
experience I had was was really powerful
it's it's like meeting God but I mean
not as like so what I think happened was
I met my own past life so like it was
literally like the first sentence or
within the first paragraph on the first
page my inner voice that was saying the
words was no longer my voice yes people
have had this experience yeah oh cool
it's a meditative practice in fact where
people learn to listen to the voice of
their thoughts and they often discover
that that voice isn't their voice yeah
so it's it's one way in which you apply
the five factors of inquiring
mindfulness to distractions especially
when the distractions are thinking so
one of the ways you want it you want to
be able to step back and be able to look
at the process which is what goes back
to what we're talking about a few
minutes ago
rather than getting involved with the
content of your thoughts that's very
hard for people to do one way to do that
is to focus not on what's being said but
on the voice of your inner speech as a
way of right still
being aware and that of itself as a
practice is valuable but it also it can
often be a revelation to people because
though I remember I taught one student
and he had been sort of I could tell he
was he was sticking with the course I
was teaching you were diligent but I
could tell his enthusiasm was kind of
middling and then I taught him this and
he sort of wet and then he came back the
next week and he was totally changed
that was him like I now see why I'm
doing this he said because I realized
for the first time that the voice inside
my head was my father's rather than mine
and he had this profound sort of
realization of aspects and dimensions of
the mind that he that he his ego
framework had not been you know directly
aware of and how that was manipulating
his behavior causing him to fall into
self-deception in ways of course that he
was not aware of and so that's a very
profound thing and of course you can
have it to varying degrees in the
Neoplatonic tradition people often
talked about anamnesis this kind of
remembering your true you know I don't
want to see your true self because that
sounds very romantic in a way I critical
but remembering right the depths
recovering we collecting the depths of
the psyche or just like two or three
really good thoughts at the same time
and I got all jumbled Alex what we're
doing right now is exactly what I was
trying to point to a few minutes ago
all right I'm not trying to convert you
when you're not trying to convert me
that's not what's happening yeah yeah we
if we give up trying to convert and get
back to conversing rather than
converting I think we can make a
tremendous amount because what we can
share is we can share processes of
insight we can choose processes of
transformation we can share processes of
connection okay so I've got one thing
I've never heard this before maybe I'm
the first guy doing this but the
fundamental shift that
seeing that's really beneficial in my
own life is changing God from a noun to
a verb yes yes yes so that's yeah that's
very much a way in which I've heard that
are often expressed in the Jewish
mystical tradition of Kabbalah because a
God's name is actually more properly
thought of as a verb than as a noun
another thing
so if only wouldn't I think like see
what see what I mean though see how if
you shift from God as a noun to God as a
verb it Orient's you towards process and
it starts to orient you towards practice
and it starts to reconfigure your
worldview so that you can rehome the
practices that you're finding personally
transformative in your own life right
right so so if we have God as a noun
like say Krishna and Krishna says oh
look at me here's my peacock feather you
know I like cow so you have to be good
to the cows that's where people get lost
is they focus on the too much on that
you know all that baggage from the now
right yes so another this I guess is not
fully relevant to like Oh a wisdom
culture I'm thinking more about
individuals what I think a lot of
Westerners are missing is a Bible and I
don't mean the Bible I mean Bible
something that to me a Bible is like
it's the rock bottom and in the ceiling
at the stand the ceiling at the same
time so it's like you it could be a text
it could be a doctrine I mean I'm I have
a very loose definition of this but it's
like it keeps you like safe and at home
like you always know where you are but
at the same time you cannot transcend
your Bible because then it's not a Bible
right but but also if you sink down all
the way into the depths
the Bible can still your Bible can still
bring you back up all the way up to the
top awesome
yeah I think that's well said so this is
especially work that I've done with
Christopher Master Pietro about trying
to reinstate witness and what what a sit
makes something a sacred text part of
what I've tried to understand that is is
instead of trying to understand it as as
the unquestioned set of doctrines
instead you understand it as a text that
you can continually go back to and the
text grows as you grow yes that's
beautiful
right and so and then we could also make
that even more dynamic in that we could
try and create something like an online
compendium of texts that many people
have found have this sacredness to them
more like because actually the Bible the
Bible is not a book it's a book of books
and there's no reason why we can't have
a book of books that we're collectively
writing and rewriting and kind of like
what Wikipedia does you know I mean
which constantly doing that so that
people as you say have a home a place
that they can but it should do it should
do both right I let's say it's you both
home them and it should also call them
from home it should give them a place
that they can return to when they need
to heal right and when they were they
need to feel connected and belonging but
it should also challenge them to go
beyond right to grow because if they
stop growing then they'll actually lose
that if we if we reformulate sacredness
as the text grows as you grow if you
stop growing and then you're actually
gonna lose sacredness because the text
is then going to just become a dead
write that sort of print yes dead set of
propositions is bad may be a way of
saying so I I'm kind of hoping we can
you because we already have and I do
this in some of my courses we all you
already have this way of getting the
collective intelligence to create a text
that no one person is the author of and
it's constantly dynamically shifting and
evolving we can do that we've all we're
already doing it in other domains for
practical educational purposes we could
improve upon it and develop it so the
edge what we're trying to educate now is
not a particular course or a particular
topic but educate the kind of education
we're talking about when we're talking
about people right becoming persons
within a community of persons people
belonging to a tradition of wisdom so
what I'm doing is since since I have my
own two Bibles Aristotle's ethics and
the bhagavad-gita which are yeah you
know they're they're not from the same
continent of course or the same culture
but for some reason it just they both
are perfect for me and they go together
at the same time and because I have just
these two texts which are not that long
to to to fully envelop my whole identity
my whole life I can put anything that
comes into my consciousness my
relationships with I just I fit it into
the into the jigsaw of these two Bibles
and I know exactly where I am
so what I'm doing that that's why my
name is ethos Ananda so ethos stands for
Aristotle basically in the West and all
that stuff and Ananda is bliss and yoga
and all that Eastern stuff right so
sorry I've been miss refer I've been
missed naming you throughout our
conversation well I have many names alex
is behind ethos is like my brand name
you know I just you know like you can
call me ethos that's fine my devotee
friends they call me ananda actually
right so
yeah so what I did was and you know I'm
a terrible marketer so I don't know how
to really push this out but I I
basically converted Aristotle's ethics
into an actual Bible so instace you know
Aristotle writes and it's very kind of
like I guess dialectic or dialogue
fashion where it's kind of like and then
let's think about this and Plato said
this and this and that so I took all the
important points and I and I numbered
them so it's just like reading a Bible
or it's like verse 1 verse 2 verse 3 I
got it down to four hundred verses so I
think for for those people who are
looking for something like that which I
was it seems like I was and I still am
my whole life it's just like Who I am
I'm like hungry for this stuff wisdom I
guess like I'm so hungry for and I'm I'm
just lucky you know it just came into my
life but I'm sure there are people out
there you know they're looking for it I
don't know how to get this to them but I
just it came to this day where I was
like I got to write this out and I gotta
just like do this you know part of my
carnal millions it's really great I
think there's lots of people who would
benefit from that and I think there's
lots of people who want to be doing that
I mean again that's what what we see
happening on these collective forums
where people try to create a collective
document rather than an individual
document all right and you know it's
really um another excellent thing is
having a master so a Bible Bible is so
cool because it you can look up to it
like it's your master but you also can
stand on it but you having like so
Aristotle is actually my master like in
in life I talked about this you have to
have a sage that you learned intimately
I just learn about you have to learn how
to intimate image
internalizing you have to learn how to
internalize a sage sounds like you have
and this is what something I also
recommend sounds like you've
internalized two sages and that and
that's a good thing that goes towards
what I was talking about before but an
ecology of practices and an ecology of
communities yeah
very much it's very important to find a
sage that you can learn about intimately
so that you can imitate and internalize
them in a profound way yes that's really
important to transforming not just your
beliefs or transforming your ability to
envision the world and to transcend
yourself okay okay so like I said before
I'm I'm mostly just lucky so I I'm I'm I
have a hard time actually figuring out
how I got here but what would you say is
the difference between like oh I'm
studying contem studying Locke and
Hobbes and they're pretty cool versus
this guy is my master like how can we
you know help people you know find that
difference I think that the sage is
somebody who is sacred in the way we
talked about that as you as you grow
they grow for you and that happens with
typically not the growth that they're
creating is not just a growth of
theoretical ability or even
philosophical understanding but it's the
kind of growth that is the comprehensive
transformation of a human being as they
aspire to be someone they are not as
they aspire to be wiser than they than
they currently are and that's what a
sages I say just somebody who reaches
you now is can reach into you but is
also reaching from where you will
eventually be that's very important yes
yes
so the language here is really important
I think there's no it always does we
have just really important taking great
care is why I'd so admire he's a dear
friend of mine my co-author and dear
friend Christopher master Pietro you
care to see any of the time dialogues
that I have with him or anything I logs
he has with guy or with Andrew Sweeney
right
he's his eloquence and precision it's
lyrical without being anyway merely
ornamental that is really really
conducive really really conducive to a
kind of profound clarity of realization
that you don't get if you just care
about the product and the bottom line of
your languages if all you're after is
again I want you to hear this point not
let's go through a process together then
you don't take care with language but
you know what
if I take language from you you lose
most of your humanity this is like a
Buddhist principle and a platonic
principle you don't take care very very
like mindful care of your language your
ultimately not taking care of your
humanity this is one thing your your
colleague Jordan Peterson did a good job
I think bringing into the the culture
it's so weird like I always knew that
but I saw him and like how he was like
really taken care of how he was speaking
and I just found myself doing that and
laughing and now I'm like I would I
would almost rather died and just then
to just find myself catching out stuff I
don't believe in saying stuff that life
is not worth living as Socrates famously
said you just said it there you'd rather
die than live the unexamined life I
agree with you and coming to a place
where you can honestly say that for
yourself I think I mean I Socrates as my
sage right I think that is one of the
crucial moments on the
the wisdom the unexamined life is not
worth living
yes that's I think that's a bit higher
than a white belt that's like a green
belt level maybe yeah I wouldn't I
wouldn't know I'm not saying that's the
realization that sets you on the path
yeah I didn't know I didn't think you
were saying that but I was just you know
China yeah sure
all right but I think it's something
that tells you that you've found your
path if you if the path that you've put
your foot upon as you honestly on
authentically come to a place where you
from the guts up not just here but from
the guts up you can say as you did so
spontaneously unauthentic Li you
basically said the unexamined life is
not worth reading
I'd rather die did not take care of how
I'm thinking and how I'm making sense of
things
that's it back to the me for example of
everything you've you said and I'm not
dismissing everything else you've said
but of everything you've said that is
what gives me the most confidence in you
right now that that moment okay
mmm mystical experiences are important
and you know from my work I talk a lot
about them in transformative a all
that's important and you know and I'm
not again you know that I'm not trying
to be dismissive of everything else you
said I know I know yeah yeah but that
that for me it's it seems like it's
because like because because a mystical
experience you know you can just have it
and forget about it but when you when
you can integrate it to the point where
yes eventually hopefully you can
spontaneously authentically say
something as I did that's a much better
sign whereas just saying your took some
mushrooms man it was dope like yeah one
thing you talked about with Jordan Hall
and others is psycho technologies and
meta psycho technologies yeah that's
right
so to me I like this language oh and
another thing about the language what we
really need and you you already
described this perfectly thing what like
sacred like like we need like like you
you did it so beautifully but if we get
it in one word so we could yeah you know
then then we can really make progress
very fast across the board you know for
religious people for non-religious
people I think it'll just like be a nice
rocker I've tried to do it with two
words so that's the best like I tried to
capture with the sense of reciprocal
opening something is opening up the
world and opening up you in a reciprocal
fashion that's it grows as you grow the
world you start just you start to it's
like a lens right right said it the eye
by which I see God is the same eye by
which God sees me right and so the
sacred is reciprocally opening it's
taking me into the depths of what's
ultimate in reality and it's taking me
it right into the depths of what's right
grounding
my entire psyche and its reciprocally
opening me up that's how I try to get it
as compact as possible so psycho
technical technology for me that
includes prayer meditation NLP CBT would
you also include all of these things yes
I would I mean I have some criticisms of
NLP but let's not get into that right
now
the the what it what is trying to be
though I'm trying to be as cautious as I
can
he's a psycho technology CBT clearly is
I think prayer is meditation
contemplation and those shouldn't be
identified they're different practices
or psycho technologies Tai Chi Chuan is
a psycho technology right yoga if it's
if it's basically created by collective
intelligence and in its standardized in
some fashion such that it is not just
learn about by you but internalize about
by you and it will have a comprehensive
effect on many domains of your life then
it's a psycho technology so the
prototypical example I have is literacy
literacy is a standardized way of
representing language right so that we
can right afford and and you know you
can deeply internalized literacy you
can't look at words and not read them by
at this point it's called the Stroop
effect right and so my if you practice
mindfulness long enough it's a
standardized way of training your
attention if you practice it long enough
it's internalized and like literacy when
you lose you think of all the domains in
which you use literacy that mindfulness
is then used usable in multiple domains
or the way I have of habitus the way I
have been Hobbiton happening my
environment talked to me by Tai Chi
Chuan that becomes also deeply
internalized and in in domain-general it
shows up in multiple domains in my life
see this is the difference between
having a
sico technology and just acquiring a
particular skill okay okay I see but
when you learn tennis right tennis isn't
designed to fit your cognition and
enhance it in a way that will be
comprehensively applied to how you can
connect to other people the world
yourself it's it's pretty much you know
in this very limited domain and again
there's nothing wrong with skills are
important they really are but a psycho
technology is much more comprehensive
and it is deeply connected it's deeply
connected to and dependent upon
collective intelligence okay okay so now
I think I see why you're saying NLP may
not be a psycho technology yeah because
there isn't really a culture for it it's
just a skill right but the thing is
though from my own experience it's a
much more effective skill than CBT but
and I've heard about that what NLP needs
to do and this is not a criticism this
is a statement although it might sound
like a criticism NLP needs to work to
get the same kind of theoretical status
and empirical evidence that CBT house
for it and it does not it has not done
that successfully I'm not saying it
can't I'm not making a criticism I'm
making a statement right yes and and I
would agree I think the reason for that
and we don't have to talk about this I
love I love NLP I find it so fascinating
the main reason I love NLP though is dr.
Bandler the co-founder reading his books
is like so much fun because half of it
he's just saying yeah I you know I
walked into some mental hospital and you
know that Guy'd schizophrenia I went Bam
Bam Bam not anymore
you know he's just like a crazy wizard
guy and anyway maybe it doesn't matter
but oh oh oh I think because it's it's
such a playful thing where it's the
focus is on just doing it the the people
who are really good at it will never
waste their time doing
studies because they'll just tear their
hair out you know and they could be
doing so much more cool stuff but we can
forget about that we should talk more
about meta psycho technology so yeah and
this and I'm glad you brought up Jordan
I mean some of the most important
conversations I've had in my life have
been with him he's a fantastic person to
have a discussion with becoming friends
and I value that a lot and it was him he
was he very me the idea of a meta psycho
technology that what I what I was
talking about and then this is what I
think dialectic ultimately is dialectic
is a meta psycho technology that
basically it puts you into right it puts
you both into the world view and into
collective intelligence in a way that is
needed if you're gonna have that
machinery at work but that we're talking
about for collecting curating and
coordinating and ecologies of practices
that that for me the ancient practice of
dialectic as it was practiced in the
Platonic and Neoplatonic schools all the
Socratic traditions is I'm trying to
understand it that's why I'm working on
my next video series after Socrates
trying to understand and this is work
that Chris and I have been writing about
ancient dialectic and I and I want to
put it into a DeeDee and I want to use
it as a template I'm not trying to go
back to the past I'm trying to salvage
what I can from the past and put that
into dialogue and I'm intending that
word with what what is emerging now all
of these practices of discourse and
collective intelligence so that we can
try to get a meta sacred technology
analogous to what dialectic was in the
ancient world which was the meta second
technology for all of the wisdom
traditions my first question is how does
dialectic give us a worldview so you
have to understand that dialectic isn't
just argumentation right so the Platonic
dialogues
the premiere place to look for what's
going on right so right there's
argumentation that's also integrated
with the process of encountering a sage
internalizing the sage having moments of
insight I mean you're a very sense of
identity called into question or being
inspired to aspire beyond yourself all
of this is being happened and it's
happening within right a forum in which
people are doing two things in a deeply
interwoven fashion what they're trying
to do is they're trying to get right
collective intelligence forming right
because in play right you're trying to
get right all the different perspectives
to talk to each other and talk having
perspectives and character talk to each
other right you what's happening in the
dialogues is you're not just seeing
competing arguments you're seeing
competing visions and competing ways of
life and they're trying to come into an
appropriate mutual transformation of
each other right right and that so
dialectic is that but dialectic is also
something you do right individually it's
something in which you're trying to
write learn how to move up and down if
you'll allow me that metaphor your
worldview in a disciplined manner so
that you can get a deep understanding of
the grammar the cognitive cultural
grammar of your worldview and so you're
doing this right if you'll allow me
these two gestural metaphors right with
your worldview and then you're doing
this with all of your perspectives and
ways of life and and then you're trying
to weave that together with
argumentation trying to get our best
discourse practices and that's why
dialectic is where you need to go if
you're going to try and write create a
new culture of wisdom
the thing is in my head like I see what
you're saying but I don't see how it can
grow from just two smart guys in the
woods so that's the question that the
question well first of all you can get
multiple people doing it and then and
this is work I'm doing especially with
both Chris and Peter Lindbergh right you
you don't want you wait you want to get
basically a program of practices you
want to start with something like and
when Russia's notion of empathy circling
that you do with for people because what
it does is it get it moves people from
bad faith to good faith dialogue and
then you might want to do some some
basic circling what the I said start
talks about where you just work on the
community and you can do that with
multiple people and then you can get
people to start to bring in some aspects
from like things like insight dialogue
and then you can bring in aspects of all
I mean I'm working on all of this right
now with people and what you can do is
you can take people through a sequence
of practices that takes them from
adversarial doctrinal conflict into what
you and I are doing here and now that's
the work I'm doing with both Chris and
Peter and you know and and and I sensed
on especially in Jordan Hall and you
know and the people within my own
particular circling group and the people
I've been meeting like Edwin and like
I'm doing participant observation I'm
actually ongoing I'm not just theorizing
going in and immersing myself in this as
much as I can
participant observation trying to get
the truth that can only be realized
through transformation and so that and
then and then taking that this is what I
mean about the bottom up and the top
down and then saying okay how could we
possibly optimally configure a program
of these practices that could take
anybody on the street and take them
through this I mean I can't give people
their motivation that's right what I can
do is write offer people here's
something that will take you there
do you not can you mention any other
concrete examples of meta psycho
technology
I'm still trying to like get a good
picture of what it is well so if you
think about an ecology of practice and
then you have to have something that
taps into the collective intelligence of
the community by which decisions can be
made for the community as a whole
so Metis meta psycho technology must
include a community it must be more than
one person right yeah
because again we're back to you can't
create a culture on your own it doesn't
make any sense so yeah so if you think
about what you see sorry I'm not trying
to be I'm not trying to force this by
being you know a fallacy of exclusion
exclusiveness but if you like let's that
like say take a look at like the church
right you know you have all of these
ecologies of practices people are
praying and they're doing all that but
what you have is you also have this way
in which you know coops of people get
together they have conclaves or they
have councils in which and what do they
do they discuss and argue that and they
try to get a process by which they're
constantly adjudicating the ecology of
practices that make up right their
tradition that's work that so right not
only do you see it within the
philosophical context what I'm talking
about you see it within the leaders
context too now the problem is how do
you do that without you know binding
people to a an unchangeable Creed so
that could be where a lot of Western
religion is failing is the psycho
technologies are still there but the
meta psycho technology is like where is
it you know like especially in in like
the Catholic Church for example
of a very well structured hierarchy
which is really excellent you know for
doing what that's good at but for for a
continuous evolution of practice it's
gonna say that this yeah I agree
so this is the trick right the
difficulty is right is you meta cycle
technology and your metaphysics are
deeply interwoven together in a way yeah
and so you need set up like patterns of
the meta Seco technology in which what
you just said is made central I would
even say made sacred which is this what
above all what this has to do is it has
to be able to evolve it has to be able
to evolve and here's what Jordan and I
have argued that and this is not a
foreclosure argument I would not dare to
pronounce on an entire religion and say
it's doomed okay I think what people who
do that are seriously either arrogant or
naivete right but naive they should say
but Jordan I and I met Chris and I also
as well right and we are not anti
religious I want that really clearly
understood but we feel that the
established religions the interweaving
of their metaphysics their mythos and
their meta psycho technology those three
are deeps it's the three MS are
interwoven together you have a two
worlds myth you have a particular kind
of supernatural istic metaphysics and
then you have a meta
psycho technology attached to all that
there's interwove inand inter defining
we think that is so bound to a rate of
change and an obsolete worldview try not
to be harsher that we do not think it is
capable of evolving in ways that are
needed for right now that's the problem
that's part of what I think Jordan means
when he's talking about you know the
blue church and the red church and he's
talking about you know and game a and
gave me that the that interweaving of
mythos metaphysics and meta secular
technologies in the established
religions
you see it happening in other religions
too right it's happening also within
Buddhism as it's coming in too deep
contact with the west's meaning crisis
is you so you see very famous people
people that I know personally some even
but like I've met them personally or
that Steven batch there or I I know him
as a colleague and a friend Ivan
Thompson people who you know are deeply
important in the Western Buddhist
community who or have both published
books on why they're not though there
are no longer Buddhists Steven is
published after Buddhism and haven't has
published why I'm not a Buddhist and
they basically write say that the idea
that Buddhism for example it has some
somehow an exception to this problem
that I'm putting my finger on
they basically criticize that and say no
it's not an exception it also is falling
prey to these kinds of problems that you
and I are talking about so we need this
is a way this takes us back to the
religion that's not a religion we have
to write we we have to tip the balance
right because because the rate of change
was what it used to be we could give
priority to being very conservative
right in the evolution but one of the
things you notice in biological
evolution is the rate of change is in
constant the rate of change has to shift
as the rate of change in the environment
shifts and we're at entered entering a
period of very rapid change and it's not
only that the change is increasing it's
the rate of change he's increasing right
and so that we can't have it
we can't have a conservative evolution
right constraint anymore we have to push
it more towards creativity it has to be
much more fluid and flowing right now
and so Jordan and I suspect that the
established religions aren't capable of
shifting the mythos metaphysics medicine
technology in such a way that it will be
able to get out of Allah
conservative bias in how it constrains
the evolution and move much more into a
creative bias in how it directs the
evolution sorry that was a lot to say
but that's a very that was very good
this very poignant spent the last
sentence that was amazing what I'm what
I'm thinking to myself is from being you
know I guess deeply involved at least to
whatever degree I have been I don't see
that change
you know I mean even but but I think
it's worse than than what I'm saying
because even if there's a religion
without a religion I think even that
will eventually have this conservative
bias again and again and one of the
hopes is that we could get it we could
get it at least enough to know what do I
want to say global enough pluralistic
enough that the conservative bias can
never take root sort of comprehensively
it would be something in which it might
do it here but right that I don't know
and now you're asking me to pronounce on
areas where I don't have very much
confidence because there's not a lot of
knowledge upon which I could make a
claim I'm trying to articulate a vision
that I think is viable and again I think
it's very important that you and you've
allowed me to take you as a
representative of the nuns again notice
what's what's sort of a point for you
that like I just don't see them capable
of doing it right which is not I don't
believe in God or I don't know yeah it's
just like no no I just
they're they seem if you'll allow me
this adjective and I don't mean it to be
insulting so I'm trying to choose it
carefully there's people like deeply
respect like paul van der clay and
jonathan pazzo and mary cohen and
jameise alright i think they matter to
me a lot and they're and they're doing
really good work but many nuns and omes
find that the established religions are
ossified
they're ossified they they don't they
don't feel that they have that vitality
of self transformation that is needed at
the fundamental level
so one thing you know you're missing
paul van der clay and jonathan pizzelle
one thing that's so cool that's happened
to me is I'm like I'm my media that I
listen to is almost entirely Christian
yes like there there are you know
Krishna devotee gurus out there but they
say the same thing every time and it's
like you know like when there's a really
good personality and I like their voice
you know that's that's great but beyond
that it's like this is why I'm very
hesitant and you heard me earlier I
expressed what I try to express a
conclusion that Jordan Hall and I share
and Kristin Master Pietro and I share
but I was very clear that I'm not
pronouncing a foreclosure on
Christianity I think I feel of trying to
that those four people was it five I
mentioned they represent what
Christianity needs to be doing but I do
not so let me say this very carefully
they represent what Christianity needs
to be doing but I am not convinced their
representative of Christianity I let me
be clear I do
I'm not calling their identification in
question I think they are sincere and
Christian no you said it very well I
think okay okay yeah and you know I hope
I'm in the same boat you know with my
own church and save whatever it's called
oh geez
there's one example that came into my
head from like there's oh there's too
many examples of this ossification it's
a good word for it like these these
incredible scholars they you know some
of these guys have PhDs and
Indian theology from you know really
excellent people they did this huge
seminar conference on bhagavad-gita and
the ancient Vedas and they like nobody
showed up from the central temple Church
authority they said oh we're busy that
doesn't fit our schedule and it's like
you can't do that you thought so I have
to be going we provide an hour and a
half is there any final question you
want to ask me or anything you want to
do of a summative nature I there is one
thing that yes Paul bender clay spoke
about this and it's stuck with me big
time
the now versus the eternal I think
that's a fundamental or the always yeah
that's so okay so I guess where does
that look okay let me get my thesis Oh
so as I was saying earlier about the
Bible like a Bible people don't have a
Bible or a sacred master another problem
here in this meaning crisis is that
people are staying too much in the now
and they they've they've kind of lost a
connection with that eternal realm which
okay I'll stop there I think that's very
important and I think that we that's why
I tried to talk about those two
dimensions this dimension is right the
dimension where we're communing and
we're trying to evolve of dialectic this
is the dimension of right the emanation
and the emergence this is the this is
the dimension of right the eternal
dimension where we're talking about the
depths of reality right so there's a
this is like the depths of reality and
this is these are this is the evolution
of realization and we need them
constantly talking together you and I
right have to be of all constantly
evolving in the now right what
needed in order to have you'll allow me
this in order to reach and help the nuns
and I don't I don't want to sound
patronizing but that's what that's what
this what I'm trying to do in some sense
right but that has to also do this right
it has to give people the sense of
connecting to what's most real
what's ultimate and so that's again why
I think dialectic is important those two
dimensions of dialectic right there the
the levels of reality and the stages of
realization have to be constantly kept
really tightly communing together in
within the process of dialectic and you
see it in Plato you you see for example
in the dialogue Socrates will come and
you'll see Socrates adjust like you can
see him evolving so he fits the person
he's talking to and he you can even see
it within the same so there's the now
right he's fitting he's fluid and
adaptive and he's not trying to bring
anything to closure or completion but
nevertheless we're getting discussions
of you know the levels of reality and
what is most you know what is most real
both of those are happening woven
together okay yeah Socrates is excellent
example okay I think so I think so too
part of what I'm trying to do is
recommend him more strongly to us as a
culture again not because I think we can
return back to the ancient Greek world
I'm deeply critical of nostalgia but
because he serves as a valuable template
for what we're trying to bring to give
birth to right now and Socrates called
himself a midwife right yeah ma model
and paradigm for trying to give birth to
something that is not yet fully born it
seems like there's a very Christian
story to it Socrates and his death yeah
and there's probably people have argued
there's probably historical connections
between the Socratic legend right and
how it gets taken up into some of the
story of Jesus's passion and that would
make a good historical sense to me given
that Jesus is he's moving around in you
know the what's I can't remember the
Greek name there's ten Greek cities he's
actually living in a very Hellenized
part of Palestine when he's doing his
mission I think it was who was it who's
arguing about he has in fact some of the
actual tropes of an itinerant cynic
philosopher he's not he is not just a
cynic philosopher I am NOT saying that
but there's clearly a cultural influence
he's also deeply influenced of course by
the Israelite prophetic tradition he
seems to be wetting them together in
some really powerful and interesting way
and so it there might have been that
Socratic model probably the enacting
Socrates not speaking Socrates but
enacting Socrates was probably an
influence on him and I like you you
fulfilled your promise and you did it in
a really graceful manner of trying to
you know simplify without dumbing down
you know with the kinds of stuff I think
about and trying to articulate further
so thank you for that
genuine thank you for that it's totally
my pleasure and my honor and it's so
beneficial for me as just from a purely
selfish you know perspective but but
others will benefit too so that's you
know it's beautiful right okay well
great pleasure meeting you even us and
please like I said send me the files and
let's do this again that sounds
excellent thank you so much professor
thank you call me John okay
okay John thanks and have a good day you
too take care